<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A diligent search amongst rulers, priests, professors, and people and a warning to all sorts high and low, that are out of the doctrine of Christ, and fear not God. Put forth by Dorothy White living in Waymouth.</title>
            <author>D. W. (Dorothy White)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65726</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1747A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217167</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828867</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828867</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33300</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65726)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33300)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1962:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A diligent search amongst rulers, priests, professors, and people and a warning to all sorts high and low, that are out of the doctrine of Christ, and fear not God. Put forth by Dorothy White living in Waymouth.</title>
                  <author>D. W. (Dorothy White)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:33300:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DILIGENT SEARCH amongſt Rulers, Prieſts, Profeſſors, and People; and a warning to all ſorts high and low, that are out of the doctrine of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and fear not God. <hi>Put forth</hi> by Dorothy White <hi>living in</hi> Waymouth.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Woe unto him that offendeth one of theſe little ones that believeth in me, ſaith Chriſt, it were better for him that he had a Mill-ſtone hanged about his neck, and that he were drownd in the depth of the Sea; it is better for that man he had never been born.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>UPon the 25th day of the ſecond moneth, 59. as I was paſſing along the ſtreet, I heard a cry in me; again on the 26th day of the ſame Moneth, the ſame cry was in me; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine on the 27th day, the ſame cry was in me, And as I was waiting upon the Lord in ſilence, the word of the Lord came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to we, ſaying, <hi>write, and again I ſay write, (As I have ſaid it ſhall come to paſſe)</hi> and this was the cry, I <hi>will confound, I will confound, the devices of this people, I will make their devices to be of none Effect, I will caſt out the councill of their Princes; O Earth, Earth, Earth hear the word of the Lord, and be warned before the cup of indignation of the Lords fierce anger is poured out upon you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though you ſtir never ſo much againſt the Lord and againſt his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, you do but kindle a fire, and at laſt you will fall into it your ſelves; Yea you ſhall run into the Caves, and dens of the Earth to hide your ſelves from the Lord, and from the glory of his Majeſty, when he ſhall appear to ſhake terribly the Earth, then ſhall your nakedneſſe be laid open before you, then shall you ſee What you have been work<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33300:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>in this dark night that is over you, a night of thick darkneſſe hath over clouded you.</p>
            <p>O you blood-thirſty Rulers of <hi>England,</hi> you Rule by the powers of Darkneſſe, you have joyned with the ſtrength of Hell to enſnare the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and to deſtroy the Lamb of God; where he doth rule, you cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the Lord of Glory, you are of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> (ſpiritually ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) for in the ſtreets of ſpiritual <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> is our Lord ſlain, For the cry of blood is found amongſt you, and the cry of your ſins is exceeding great, it hath aſcended to the eares of the Lord God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, And all the ſacrifices that you offer up to the Lord is but a corrupted thing, the Lord is wearyed with your abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Therefore a warning from the Lord God unto you, Prieſts, Rulers, people &amp; profeſſors, while there is a call to repentance, for now hath the Lord called all to repentance, and hath once more warned you whiles the day of mercy laſteth, for <hi>Sodom and Ghomorah</hi> of old were warned to repent of the Judgements that ſhould come upon them, and they repented not, and were deſtroyed. And you hath the Lord war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to repent, and once more hath he warned you, before the day of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation come, wherein there will be no place for repentance found; for now is the Lord God working his mighty work in the Earth, he is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing Kingdomes, and ruling the Nations as with a rod of Iron, he is bringing down the mighty from their ſears, he is throwing down Kings from their Thrones; And all you high and loughty ones, you fruitleſſe branches, you will the Lord cut down with the ſword of his power; and all you briers and brambles of the Earth that are now fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lamb of God, you ſhall be as fewel prepared for the fite in the day of the Lords fierce indignation, for a day of ſorrow, anguiſh and pain and great tribulation ſhall come upon all fleſh, and upon all that are out of Covenant with God, for great is the God of <hi>Abraham</hi> of <hi>Iſack</hi> and of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and who ſhall be able to withſtand his power: For now is he come to eſtabliſh his Throne in righteouſneſſe, upon the top of all Thrones, yea, he will ſit as King upon his holy hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> for <hi>Jacobs</hi> God hath appeared, and his light now ſhineth, and hath broken through dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and hath broken the bonds of iniquity, and is ariſing with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in his wings, on them that do believe.</p>
            <p>None knoweth the Father but the Son, and him to whom the Son revealeth him, and him that hath the Son, hath the Father alſo, And the Son is the light and life of men, that all through him might believe, and have everlaſting life. For now is God appearing in power and in Majeſty, and through his Son is he drawing all men unto him, that would come in unto him, who is the light that enlightneth every man that cometh into the world, this is him, whom the Prophets propheſied of, and the ſame which <hi>Iohn</hi> bare witneſſe to, and ſaid that he was not that light, but was ſent to bear witneſſe of that light. <hi>This is the true light, and he doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world.</hi> The ſame do we bear witneſſe to now. <hi>The world was made by him, and the world knew him not, he came to his own, and his own received him not, But to as many as did, to them he gave power to become the ſons of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33300:2"/>
            <p>Now to you that are ſeeking abroad, for that you have loſt at home in your own houſes, (within you) you muſt turne in again to the light of Chriſt, the way to the Father, and Covenant of God. All that are out of the light, are out of Covenant with God, <hi>For he is given for a covenant of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight unto the Gentiles, and for ſalvation to the ends of the Earth: This is my welbeloved Son, hear ye him in all things,</hi> ſaith God. <hi>This is the true Prprophet, and all that will not hear this prophet, are to be cut off from the Earth.</hi> And all other prophets do we deny, that do run and never were ſent of God, theſe ſhall not profit the people at all, they are the wolves, they have gotten the ſheeps <hi>cloathing but inwardly they are ravening wolves by their fruits you may know them;</hi> Theſe are the deceivers of the Nation, upon theſe will the Lord God power out the cup of his fierce indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the fire of his jealouſie is kindled againſt them, and he will take vengeance on them, for they are murtherers of the Son of God, for the day of terrible judgement is drawn near unto them, a day of howling and of bitter lamentation, a cup of vengeance will the Lord God power out upon them; woe, woe, woe, from the Lord God unto them, they ſhall down into the depth of Hell without ſpeedy repentance; a warning from the Lord God unto you Prieſts of <hi>England,</hi> hear, hear, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der before the fiery wrath of the Lord God fall upon you; fear, fear, &amp; tremble for fear of the Lord God of Hoſts, for you hath the Lord God a great &amp; mighty controverſie with, againſt you, for now is the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>to try the ſons of men, and to purifie the ſons of</hi> Levi, <hi>and to purifie them as fine gold that hath been tried ſeven times in the fire,</hi> And he is purifying of his temple that he may dwel therein, as he hath ſaid, <hi>I will walk in them, I wil dwel in them, I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people, and it ſhall come to paſſe ſaith the Lord, that I will raiſe up the righteous branch of</hi> David, <hi>and a King ſhall rule and proſper, and of his Dominion there ſhall be no end. And this is the name they ſhall call him (the Lord our righteouſneſſe) For many ſhall come from the Eaſt, and from the Weſt, and ſhall ſit down with</hi> Abraham, <hi>with</hi> Iſaack, <hi>and with</hi> Jacob, <hi>that are the ſeed of</hi> Abraham <hi>borne after the ſpirit. In</hi> Iſaack <hi>ſhall the ſeed be bleſſed,</hi> That is, not the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> that is born after the fleſh, for that is the perſecuting birth, he that is born after the fleſh, perſecuteth him that is born after the ſpirit, <hi>Cain</hi> was a murtherer from the beginning, <hi>Cain</hi> offered up ſacrifice, yet he ſlew his brother <hi>Abel,</hi> the juſt one, born after the ſpirit, but <hi>Caines</hi> ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice was not accepted with the Lord, but the blood of righteous <hi>Abel</hi> cried from the Earth for vengeance to the Lord, although you offer many ſacrifices, yet doth not the Lord regard them, you are of <hi>Cains</hi> ſtock, you perſecute the juſt one born after the ſpirit, you murther your brother, but the blood of him cryeth from the Earth for vengeance to me ſaith the Lord, to be taken on you, <hi>Woe unto the drunkards of</hi> Ephraim, <hi>that are not drunk with wine, nor ſtrong bear, but with the blood of Saints,</hi> you muſt drink the cup of wrath, you heap up wrath upon your ſelves, you heap up deſtruction upon deſtruction, for the all ſeeing eye of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds you and your ſecret intents, let them be never ſo ſecretly acted, he doth ſee your waies, and he wil reward you openly, a juſt recompence according to your deeds of darkneſſe, for the powers of heaven ſhall move, and there ſhal be earth-quakes in divers places, the powers of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven doth move, the Earth doth tremble before the Lord, the mountains
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33300:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>melts at his preſence, he doth not ſhake the Earth onely, but the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens alſo: <hi>Like as the lightning cometh out of the Eaſt and ſhineth into the Weſt, ſo ſhall the coming of the Son of man be;</hi> And we have ſeen his coming and we are built upon the <hi>Rock, and the gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt us.</hi> Although many are ſaying, there are a people riſen up now that go about to turne the world upſide down, if we let them go on; But I tell you it is not the people, but it is the power of God, for he is come to turne the World upſide down. That that, which hath ruled, over may be brought down under, and that which hath been of low degree, may be raiſed up by the power of God, to rule and have the dominion; for God is coming to throw down the kingdom of Anti chriſt that hath had the dominion, and hath ruled in the hearts of men, the prince of the powers of darkneſſe, that rules in the hearts of the children of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience that obey not the Goſpel of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For kingdom ſhall riſe againſt Kingdom, and nation ſhall riſe againſt Nation, for there ſhall be wars and rumors of wars on the Earth, and when you ſee thoſe things coming to paſſe, then is the end neer, behold the time cometh ſaith the Lord, that I will draw near unto judgement,</hi> I <hi>will be a ſwift witneſſe againſt the double minded, and all that are covered with an unrighteous covering;</hi> for all coverings ſhall be too narrow, for <hi>Sion</hi> ſhal be ploughed as a field, the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-ground turned up, &amp; the frutleſs branches burned, for now is the Lord comming to require fruit of his vine-yard, <hi>Behold I will tell you of my be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved concerning his vine-yard, my beloved hath a vineyard upon a very fruitful mountain,</hi> &amp; <hi>he looked for fruit and it brought forth wild grapes, I wil tel you what I will do with my vine-yard, I will take away the hedg about it, I will alſo forbid the clouds of heaven that it ſhould not rain.</hi> Now man in the beginning was created in the Image of God, &amp; he was the vine-yard of God, placed in a very fruitfull mountain, as long as he ſtood there he was in union with God, but when he went our into tranſgreſſion, he loſt the union with God, then he brought forth the wild grapes, he became the degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted plant, degenerated from his maker, this is the ſtate of fallen man, ſo long as he is in tranſgreſſion, let him profeſſe what he will, yet he is naked and aſhamed to appear before the Lord, when the Lord calleth to him to return, becauſe he is not covered with that righteous cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that he was in, in the beginning, but he hath ſown to himſelf figg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaves to cover his nakedneſs, that is a ſelf-righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>God that made Heaven and Earth, and created all things hath looked down from heaven, and is beholding the children of men, and is calling to them to return from the evil of their wayes, by his Son Chriſt the light and life of men, and <hi>doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world,</hi> he is not come to deſtroy life but to ſave life, but he is not come to deſtroy ſin in the fleſh; for this very end and purpoſe, was the Son of God made manifeſt in the fleſh, that he might deſtroy the works of the devil, &amp; by the light is his work manifeſted, <hi>for whatſoever manifeſteth, the ſame is light,</hi> and as it is received and believed in, and followed, and obeyed; it will lead out of ſin, and out of tranſgreſſion, and it will lead, unto the Father of lights, from whence it came: as he ſaid <hi>I came out from the Father, and I teſtifie of the Father to the world;</hi> Again <hi>I ſhall leave
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33300:3"/>the world, and go to the Father;</hi> So all that come unto him that is the light, he leadeth out of the world, and leadeth to the Father again, <hi>for he was given for a leader to the people, and for a light unto the Gentiles, and for ſalvation to the ends of the earth,</hi> unto the people that ſate in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hath the light ſhined, and a glorious light hath appeared to them that ſate in the ſhadow of death, and hath given them the knowledge of the Father, in the face of the Son, <hi>he hath given us the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the light that <hi>John</hi> bear witneſs too, <hi>John</hi> ſaid <hi>he was not that light, but was ſent to bear witneſs of that light, and ſaid, that was the true light, that lighteth every man that cometh, into the world,</hi> Yet <hi>John</hi> was <hi>a burning and a ſhining light, John</hi> was in priſon when Chriſt came, for <hi>hearing witneſs to the light,</hi> and <hi>for preaching re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> and <hi>for crying in the wilderneſs, prepare the way of the Lord, and make his paths ſtraight</hi> in the deſert; for they that are not come to the light of Chriſt <hi>within them,</hi> are yet in the wilderneſs: They have not heard the cry of <hi>John,</hi> nor made ſtraight the way of the Lord, nor regarded his cry that calleth to repentance, but he is kept in priſon by them that deny the light, but now is the light come, and doth rule in the hearts of the children of light, and the day hath dawned, and the day-ſtar is riſen in our hearts, that leadeth to the Lamb of God, and the Lamb ſhall get the victory; and the Lamb ſhall have the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, for he is come to rule in the earth, and all ſhall throw down their Crowns at his feet, for now is God exalting him, over all the Kingdoms of the world, and he ſhall ſit in Majeſty, and rule the Nations with the word of his power; for now is the Goſpel of peace to be preached unto all Nations, and peoples, kindreds, and tongues, to all that dwell on the face of the whole earth; for now hath the trumpet of the Lord ſounded, and an Alarum is gone forth of his holy mountain to all that dwell on the earth, <hi>to worſhip him in the ſpirit and in the truth,</hi> for ſuch is the Lord calling to worſhip him, For behold now is the day wherein <hi>the Lord will not be worſhipped at Jeruſalem, nor in this mountain, nor at Samaria, but he will be worſhipped in the ſpirit and in the truth:</hi> for when the woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> was drawing water at the well of <hi>Samaria,</hi> Chriſt ſaid unto her, <hi>if thou hadſt asked of me, I would have given thee living water, that whoſoever drinketh thereof ſhould never thirſt again;</hi> then ſhe left her water-pot and went into the City, &amp; ſaid, behold a man that told me all that ever I did: is not this the Chriſt? Then ſhe left the water of <hi>Samaria</hi> when the living water was come, and when ſhe had taſted of the water of life, ſhe left <hi>Samaria,</hi> and worſhipped there no longer.</p>
            <p>Behold now is the Lord coming to make a ſeparation between thoſe that worſhip him in the ſpirit and in truth, from them that worſhip him not in the ſpirit and in the truth, for that is the falſe worſhip that is out of the truth, &amp; there the deceivers worſhip, the deceivers went out from the truth; they do lead people into error, and deceive them for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt gain. O Iſrael, thy leaders hath deceived thee, they have cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted thy footſtepts before the Lord, therefore is the Lord coming to ſcatter them with the whirlwind of his wrath, They ſhall be as chaff that is to be burned with unquenchable fire, in the day of the Lords fierce indignation.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:33300:4"/>
            <p>Therefore a warning from the Lord unto you Rulers, Profeſſors, and people in the Town of <hi>Waymouth,</hi> a warning from the Lord God unto you that are out of the light of the Son of God, that are yet in rebellion againſt the Son of God the light of the world.</p>
            <p>To you that are ſeeking the living among the dead, in vain do you ſeek there, for the living God you do not ſerve, whiles you live in ſin, and ſay you muſt live in ſin whiles you are upon earth, this is contrary to the doctrine of Chriſt that the Apoſtles Preached, and ſaid they were ſent <hi>to turn people from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan unto God;</hi> and they preached the Goſpel freely, as they had received freely, for they Preached <hi>the Goſpel of Chriſt</hi> to be <hi>the power of God,</hi> and they ſpake as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt, and from the Revelation of Chriſt in them; Theſe be the true Miniſters of Chriſt, that Preach Chriſt revealed in them, they are ſent of God, and this is the difference between the Miniſters of Chriſt, and if Antichriſt, that run and are not ſent of God, they tell the people of a Chriſt that they muſt believe in, that dyed for their ſins, when they themſelves do not believe in him, nor know the light of Chriſt in them, he died to ſave his people from their ſins, not that they ſhould live in their ſins, &amp; they that know him ſo far, knows him to be their Saviour, and they to be ſaved by him, and redeemed from all iniquity; They can ſay their Redeemer liveth in them, and they are tranſlated from death unto life, and ſet free by the Son; <hi>As many as are ſet free by the Son, are free indeed, they are no more under the Law, but under grace, The Law came by Moſes, But grace and truth came by Jeſus Chriſt; had it not been for the law we bad not known ſin; The law is light,</hi> and this is the law of God written in our hearts, as he ſaid, <hi>I will write my law in their hearts, and will put my ſpirit in their inward parts, and they ſhall not depart from me, I will give them a heart of fleſh, I will take away their ſtony heart and they ſhall be my people, and I will be their God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold now is the <hi>Lord</hi> gathering in his choſen ſeed, choſen before the foundation of the world, that ſhall ſerve him in truth, and in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; for righteouſneſs ſhall flow down as a ſtream, and juſtice ſhall Rule in the earth, and judgement ſhall be ſet up in the earth, that the inhabitants thereof may learn righteouſneſs, for judgement is he come who is the light, that thoſe that do not ſee, may ſee, and thoſe that do ſee, may be made blind; and <hi>he is come not to bring peace on the earth, but a ſword,</hi> to cut down and deſtroy the man of ſin; and this is the work he is doing, to deſtroy ſin in the fleſh: In them where ſin yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth, there Chriſt is not known to deſtroy the works of the devil, for that end was he manifeſted in the fleſh, <hi>for this is the miſtery of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, Chriſt manifeſted in the fleſh,</hi> for he that revealeth the Father is the Son, and the Son is the light, and by him are the ſecrets of God revealed to them that fear him; But them that are out of the light, they know not the ſecrets of God, they are out of the fear of God: For <hi>he that believeth, out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of living water, ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to eternal life,</hi> the everlaſting fountain ſhall be opened unto him, and the ſprings of life unſtopt, that all may come and drink freely: for <hi>Chriſt came not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance,</hi> and to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtop the ears of the deaf, and to open the eyes of the blind, and to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33300:4"/>raiſe the dead to life; <hi>I am the reſurrection and the life</hi> ſaid Chriſt, <hi>he that believeth in me ſhall never ſee death; and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day; But he that walketh in darkneſs and fayes he hath fellowſhip with God, he is a lyar and does not the truth, but if we walk in the light, as he is in the light, then have we fellow-ſhip one with another, and the blood of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This to you that are mocking at the light and ſcoffing at the ſpirit of the Lord, a woful day is coming upon you, a day of terrible vengeance upon all that are found ſtriving againſt the Lord, and reſiſting his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, a day of deſolation, and of ſwift deſtruction, a cup of endleſſe wrath will the Lord pour out upon you, unleſs you ſpeedily repent; for the day of vengeance is drawing near you, for God will not be mocked; for the <hi>Lord</hi> that created all things upon the whole earth, at ſeveral times moved me to go into your ſteeple ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe, in the time of your worſhip, fore-ſeeing the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat miſery and deſolation that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon you, ſhewn to me by the <hi>Lord;</hi> But before I could deliver what the <hi>Lord</hi> ſent me to deliver, they ſet hands on me, and put me forth, and carried me to the priſon, and told me they would put me in, but did not; It did not lie in their power to do it; but when I came up again, the <hi>Lord</hi> led me in again, and many ſtrived againſt me, and put me out again before I had done delivering the meſſage of the <hi>Lord;</hi> Again the word of the <hi>Lord</hi> came unto me, <hi>Go and ſay the Lord of hoſts hath ſent thee to bear witneſs againſt the Idol ſhepherds;</hi> But many ſtrived againſt me, but wo from the <hi>Lord God</hi> unto them that ſtrive to hinder the meſſenger of the Lord: Again the word of the <hi>Lord</hi> came unto me: <hi>Go cry againſt the fooliſh Prophets that Preacheth lies in my name,</hi> by the power of the <hi>Lord</hi> I was brought thither, to fulfill his will, and to deliver his word faithfully, which word is like a fire, and like a hammer, that breaketh the rocks in pieces that cannot be ſtaved: But two feirce ſpirited men ſtirred up with much wrath came and haled me forth, and ſaid it was the Devils work, and that I looked like the Devil; but they are his ſervants that doth his work, and they fight for their maſter, as the high prieſts ſervants did of old: But woe unto all them that are found fighting againſt their maker, woe from the Lord God unto you, that have ſtrived to hinder the meſſinger of the Lord, you ſhal know in the day of the Lord, when he ſhall appear to take a count of your actions in this thing then ſhal you know that I was ſent of God; then ſhall the light in your conſciences be awakened and then ſhall you ſee what you have been doing; And then ſhall you witneſſe for me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the juſt judge of heaven, that I was ſent by him, and that I cleared my conſcience to you, whether you will hear it or no, it will ſtand a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt you in the day of wrath, when wrath ſhall be poured out without mercy upon the ungodly, and upon the rebellious, and ſuch as have rejected the councell of the <hi>Lords</hi> for woe and miſery is coming upon ſuch, that are yet rebelling againſt the Son of God, the light of the world, a warning from the Lord <hi>God</hi> unto ſuch, whilſt the day of repentance laſts, before the time come that repentance be hid from their eyes, and that they go down to the grave in ſorrow, and periſh in the pit. <hi>For judgement is begun at the houſe of God and it muſt go through all, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33300:5"/>end in the deſtruction of the wicked:</hi> For the wicked ſhall be turned into Hell, and all that forget <hi>God:</hi> For upon the ungodly ſhall rain ſnares, fire and brimſtone, ſtormes and tempeſt, this ſhall be their portion to drink, for the righteous Lord loveth righteouſneſſe, and his countenance will behold that which is juſt; for <hi>God</hi> is in the congregation of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and they ſhall abide with him for ever.</p>
            <p>The ſervant of the <hi>Lord</hi> fore-writ of certain men <hi>were craftily crept into houſes, leading ſilly women captive, laden with ſin, &amp; with divers luſts having the form of godlineſſe, but denying the power thereof, ever learning, but never able to come to the knowledge of the truth:</hi> Theſe are the men he fore-writ of, that are craftily crept into houſes, (and calles them churches) but they are Wells without water, <hi>and clouds without rain carryed about with a tempeſt;</hi> And theſe are the deceivers that calls houſes Churches, and theſe are the ſilly women led by them captive (marke) captive into ſin: Divers luſts is divers ſins, &amp; they that are led in them, are led into captivity, (mark) they are ever learning and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth, whilſt they are led into ſin, they are ever learning, and never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to know the truth, <hi>They have the form of godlineſſe,</hi> but they want the power; and the power is the truth, and the truth is the way and they that want the power are out of the way (mark) and the way is the Son, and the Son ſets free. And <hi>as many as are led by the ſpirit of God, are the Sons of God,</hi> and them that the Son <hi>ſets free,</hi> are <hi>free indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>
               <hi>This is to be ſent abroad amongſt the inhabitants of</hi> Way<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mouth <hi>as a warning from the Lord God unto them, before the day of deſolation come; that is drawing neer to them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are out of the fear of God, and are yet gainſaying the tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> for a juſt and lawful tryall wherby they might come to the light of Chriſt within them, and try their way, to ſee how it differs from the way of God and to return from the evill of it, and return into the truth, and feel after God, and find him.</hi>
            </trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>given forth by <hi>Dorothy White.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Written in <date>the third Moneth, 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33300:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
